Guide to the New-York Historical Society Geographic Images Collection circa 1600-2006 PR 20
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society Geographic Images collection, formerly Geographic File
ca. 1600-2006
1850-1950
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society. Library
PR 20
135 Linear feet (160 boxes; 124 drawers of flat files)
This collection, formerly know as the Geographic File, includes prints, photographs, and some newspaper clippings of street views and buildings in the five boroughs of New York City (Series I through V), arranged by location or by type of structure. Series VI contains views of the United States outside of New York City, and Series VII consists of views outside of the United States.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Material is a combination of gifts and purchases. Individual dates or information can be found on the verso of most items.
Conditions Governing Access
For more information on making arrangements to consult the collection, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Scope and Contents
This collection is an artificial collection created over the course of many years in the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections. Small donations of prints or photographs of views of geographic locations have been filed here. The collection contains, in addition to prints and photographs, some newspaper clippings, some reproductions of paintings and other items in the N-YHS Museum collection, and some ephemera.
The collection is divided into seven series:
Series I: New York City Views - Manhattan
Series II: New York City Views - the Bronx
Series III: New York City Views - Brooklyn
Series IV: New York City Views - Queens
Series V: New York City Views - Staten Island
Series VI: American Views
Series VII: Foreign Views
Within each series, material is separately housed by size. Boxes hold material smaller than approximately 12 x 14 inches. Larger material is housed flat in folders in drawers. Oversize material is generally larger than 30 x 40 inches.
Boxed material is described to the folder level. Some larger material has been described to the item level. Oversize material is all described to the item level, to facilitate use and reduce unnecessary handling. See individual series descriptions for more cataloging information.
Series I- through Series V, New York City Views is arranged in an organizational structure first by borough, and then by topic of the view.
AERIAL views are those taken from airplanes or from the top of a tall building or birds-eye views (generally 19th-century prints). Aerial views of lower Manhattan include views of the World Trade Center. Aerial views of midtown include views of the Empire State Building and the Chrysler Building. Aerial views of uptown include images of Central Park, Grant's Tomb, Riverside Drive and Riverside Park. Harbor views are those which show the shore and skyline from the water, or from across some body of water.
RIVERS, ISLANDS, and BRIDGES are arranged alphabetically. Most buildings on islands (for example, asylums on Roosevelt Island) are filed under general Buildings headings. It behooves researchers to look under both headings to be sure of complete coverage.
STREET SCENES are views along streets and avenues. Some show a small portion of one block, some show several blocks. For views that specifically spotlight one building, search under BUILDINGS. However, researchers should also search the street scenes for other images of a specific building, especially those which may also show surrounding buildings and street and sidewalk traffic. Street scenes are arranged alphabetically or numerically. A few named squares have their own folder (i.e. Herald Square and Times Square).
PARKS and GARDENS include images of parks and gardens, some now defunct, throughout New York City. A few gardens run as commercial enterprises, such as Elgin's Botanic Garden can be found here.
BUILDINGS are prints or photographs that spotlight a specific building. Churches, synagogues and other houses of worship are filed alphabetically by name following the organization provided in David Dunlap's encyclopedic work From Abyssinian to Zion, which is available for reference. Government buildings include police and fire stations. Residences are filed alphabetically by the last name of the owner, or by their own name, if applicable. Cross- references have been provided in those cases. Named apartment complexes are filed in alphabetically with residences, and unnamed apartment buildings can be found at the end of the run.
TRANSPORTATION includes images of all sorts of transportation found within the boundaries of New York City. For more general transportation (i.e. generic railroad images), look in the Subject File (PR 068). This category mainly includes images of buses, carriages, elevated railroads and subway images. Images of shipping boats can sometimes be found in Harbor Views, and also in the Maritime History File (PR 100).
EVENTS include views of special events, such as parades, funeral processions, and celebrations. Researchers looking for parade images should also check street scenes for those streets that are often parade routes, such as Broadway and Fifth Avenue.
Material housed in boxes includes many photos by Beecher Ogden, and also a great many images (most copy photographs) collected, and donated, by George Bagoe.
Material housed flat has been separated into two categories based on format: Prints and Photographs. Within each format, material has been arranged into the above categories. Each image filed under the Buildings categories is separately listed in the finding aid below. In other categories, attempts have been made to provide more specific information about images in each folder, to reduce browsing and encourage more specific use.
Series VI. American Views is arranged alphabetically by state. Within states, views of cities are also arranged alphabetically. In the boxed views, if five or more views of a city exist, that city received its own folder. Within each city, additional folders were also created for buildings, etc. with five or more views.
Series VII. Foreign Views is arranged alphabetically by country. Current (as of 2006), and not contemporaneous, names of countries were used. Each country for which there is a view is listed. In the boxed views, if five or more views of a city within a country exist, that city received its own folder.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into seven series:
Series I: New York City Views - Manhattan
Series II: New York City Views - the Bronx
Series III: New York City Views - Brooklyn
Series IV: New York City Views - Queens
Series V: New York City Views - Staten Island
Series VI: American Views
Series VII: Foreign Views
Within each series, material is separately housed by size. Boxes hold material smaller than approximately 12 x 14 inches. Larger material is housed flat in folders in drawers. Oversize material is generally larger than 30 x 40 inches.
Boxed material is described to the folder level in all series.
Flat material in Series I-V (New York City Views) has been described to the item level.
Oversize material in Series I-V (New York City Views) is described to the item level, to facilitate use and reduce unnecessary handling.
See individual series descriptions for more cataloging information.
Series I- through Series V, New York City Views is arranged in an organizational structure first by borough, and then by topic of the view.
Series VI. American Views is arranged alphabetically by state. Within states, views of cities are also arranged alphabetically. In the boxed views, if five or more views of a city exist, that city received its own folder. Within each city, additional folders were also created for buildings, etc. with five or more views.
Series VII. Foreign Views is arranged alphabetically by country. Current (as of 2006), and not contemporaneous, names of countries were used. Each country for which there is a view is listed. In the boxed views, if five or more views of a city within a country exist, that city received its own folder.
Buildings -- New York (State); Buildings -- United States.; Commercial buildings -- New York (State) -- New York.; Historic buildings -- New York (State) -- New York.; Public buildings -- New York (State) -- New York.; Public spaces -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Streets -- New York (State) -- New York.; Street life -- New York (State) -- New York.; Subways -- New York (State) -- New York.; Transportation -- New York (State) -- New York.; Photographic prints.; Lithographs.; Engravings (prints)
- Series I: New York City Views - Manhattan
  Scope and Contents
  Series I New York City Views - Manhattan is arranged in an organizational structure by topic of the view. VIEWS include aerial views (those taken from airplanes or from the top of a tall building) and birds-eye views (generally 19th-century prints), as well as general views.
  Harbor views are those which show the shore and skyline of Manhattan from the water, or from across some body of water. Some river and harbor views that show more than one borough are filed here. If the view is mainly of another borough, it will be filed therein. For views of the Manhattan harbors and piers from within the city, also look under Rivers.
  RIVERS, ISLANDS, and BRIDGES are arranged alphabetically. Most buildings on islands (for example, asylums on Roosevelt Island) are filed under general Buildings headings. It behooves researchers to look under both headings to be sure of complete coverage.
  STREET SCENES are views along streets and avenues. Some show a small portion of one block, some show several blocks. For views that specifically spotlight one building, search under BUILDINGS. However, researchers should also search the street scenes for other images of a specific building, especially those which may also show surrounding buildings and street and sidewalk traffic. Street scenes are arranged alphabetically or numerically. Researchers interested in specific areas should also consult surrounding streets, such as the avenues and appropriate cross streets.
  PARKS and GARDENS include images of parks and gardens, some now defunct.
  BUILDINGS are prints or photographs that spotlight a specific building. Churches and houses of worship are filed alphabetically by name following the organization provided in David Dunlap's encyclopedic work From Abyssinian to Zion, which is available for reference.
  NOTE: Churchesand Synagogues also includes temples, other houses of worship, convents, retreat houses, and cemeteries. Government buildings include police and fire stations. Residences are filed alphabetically by the last name of the owner, or by their own name, if applicable. Cross-references have been provided in those cases. Named apartment complexes are filed in alphabetically with residences, and unnamed apartment buildings can be found at the end of the run.
  TRANSPORTATION includes images of all sorts of transportation found within the boundaries of New York City. For more general transportation (i.e. generic railroad images), look in the Subject File (PR 068). This category mainly includes images of buses, carriages, elevated railroads and subway images. Images of shipping boats can sometimes be found in Harbor Views, and also in the Maritime History File (PR 100).
  EVENTS include views of special events, such as parades, funeral processions, celebrations, and fairs. Researchers looking for parade images should also check street scenes for those streets that are often parade routes, such as Broadway and Fifth Avenue.
  Material housed in boxes includes many photos by Beecher Ogden, and also a great many images (most copy photographs) collected and donated by George Bagoe.
  Material housed flat has been separated into two categories based on format: Prints and Photographs. Within each format, material has been arranged into the above categories. Each image filed under the Buildings categories is separately listed in the finding aid below. In other categories, attempts have been made to provide more specific information about images in each folder, to reduce browsing and encourage more specific use.
  - Subseries IA: MANHATTAN - BOXED MATERIAL
    - Manhattan - Boxed Material - Views
      - Aerial Views of Lower Manhattan Taken from Planes (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Aerial Views of Lower Manhattan Taken from Airplanes (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Aerial Views Showing Construction of World Trade Center (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Aerial Views of Lower Manhattan Taken from Rooftops (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Aerial Views of Lower Manhattan Taken from Rooftops (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Aerial Views of Lower Manhattan Taken From Rooftops (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Aerial Views of Midtown (1st to 59th Streets) (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Aerial Views of Uptown (59th Street and North) (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Birdseye Views (Prints) (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Harbor Views, 17th Century (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Harbor Views, 18th Century (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Harbor Views, 18th Century: Burgis View (1717-1718) (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Harbor Views, 18th Century: Carwitham View (1731-1736) (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Harbor Views, 19th Century (Prints) (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Harbor Views, 19th Century (Prints): New York From Staten Island (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Harbor Views, 19th Century (Prints): New York from Weehawken (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Harbor Views, 19th Century (Photos) (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Harbor Views, 20th Century (Prints) (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Harbor Views, 20th Century (Photos) (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Harbor Views, 20th Century (Photos) (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Harbor Views, 20th Century (Photos) (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Snapshots Taken from Circle Line Tour (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Night Views (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Night Views (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Winter Views (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - General Views: Manhattan Island Milestones (Photos by Richard Koke) (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - General Views: Bourne Views of New York City (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - General Views: Intimate Sketches of New York (by Vernon Howe Bailey) (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - General Views: Intimate Sketches of New York (by Vernon Howe Bailey) (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - General Views: Then and Now Series, Ye Olde Settlers' Association (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - General Views: Photographs by Harry V. Mitchell, 1910-1925 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - General Views: Photographs by Robert C. Weinberg, ca. 1930 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - General Views: Photographs by Robert C. Weinberg, ca. 1930 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - General Views: Composite views and multiple scenes (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - General Views: Souvenir View Books (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - General Views: City Guide Books, Albums & Magazines (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - General Views: City Guide Books, Albums & Magazines (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Manhattan - Boxed Material - Rivers
      - East River - Hell Gate (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - East River - Hell Gate - Flood Rock Explosion (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - East River - Shore (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - East River - Waterfront (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - East River - Waterfront (Photos by Beecher Ogden) (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Harlem River (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Hudson River (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Hudson River - Piers (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Hudson River - Waterfront (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - Hudson River - West 59th to West 128th Street (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Spuyten Duyvil Creek (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Manhattan - Boxed Material - Islands
      - Ellis Island (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Governor's Island (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Bedloe's (now Liberty) Island (Prints) (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Bedloe's (now Liberty) Island (Photographs) (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - North Brother Island - Roosevelt Hospital (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Randall's Island (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Roosevelt Island (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Ward's Island (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Manhattan - Boxed Material - Bridges
      includes the Bayonne Bridge and Verrazano Bridge (which are not in Manhattan, but are part of the network of bridges which connect NYC and the greater New York area).
      - Bayonne Bridge (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - Brooklyn Bridge - construction (Box 6, Folder 10-11)
      - Brooklyn Bridge - railway (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - Brooklyn Bridge - photographs (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
      - Brooklyn Bridge - prints (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Brooklyn Bridge - misc. (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Broadway Bridge (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Dyckman's Bridge (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - George Washington Bridge - construction (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - George Washington Bridge (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - George Washington Bridge - ephemera (Box 7, Folder 11)
      - Harlem Bridge (Box 7, Folder 12)
      - Hellgate Bridge (Box 7, Folder 13)
      - Henry Hudson Bridge (Box 7, Folder 14)
      - High Bridge - photographs (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
      - High Bridge - prints (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - High Bridge - misc. (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Manhattan Bridge (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Macomb's Dam Bridge (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - New York and Putnam Railroad Bridge (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - Queensboro Bridge (59th St. Bridge/Ed Koch Queensboro Bridge) (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - Third Avenue Bridge (Box 8, Folder 9)
      - Verrazano Bridge (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - Washington Bridge (Harlem River) (Box 8, Folder 11-12)
      - Whitestone Bridge (Box 8, Folder 13)
      - Williamsburg Bridge (Box 8, Folder 14)
      - Willis Avenue Bridge (Box 8, Folder 15)
      - Bridges - Other (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Manhattan - Boxed Material - Street Views
      - Abingdon Square (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Academy Street (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Allen Street (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - Amity Lane (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - Amsterdam Avenue (formerly Tenth Avenue) (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Amsterdam Avenue (formerly Tenth Avenue) (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - Amsterdam Avenue (formerly Tenth Avenue) (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - Ann Street (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Arden Street (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - Astor Place (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - Bank Street (Box 9, Folder 11)
      - Barclay Street (Box 9, Folder 12)
      - Barrow Street (Box 9, Folder 13)
      - Baruch Place (formerly Goerck Street) (Box 9, Folder 14)
      - Battery Place (Box 9, Folder 15)
      - Baxter Street (formerly Orange Street) (Box 9, Folder 16)
      - Bayard Street (Box 9, Folder 17)
      - Beach Street (Box 9, Folder 18)
      - Beaver Street (Box 9, Folder 19)
      - Bedford Street (Box 9, Folder 20)
      - Beekman Place (Box 9, Folder 21)
      - Beekman Street (Box 9, Folder 22)
      - Bennett Avenue (Box 9, Folder 23)
      - Birmingham Street (Box 9, Folder 24)
      - Bleecker Street (Box 9, Folder 25-27)
      - Bond Street (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Bowery (Box 10, Folder 2-4)
      - Broad Street (views depicting Broad Street prior to 1800) (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - Broad Street (19th century views) (Box 10, Folder 6)
      - Broad Street (20th century views) (Box 10, Folder 7)
      - Broadway ("Both Sides of Broadway") (Box 10, Folder 8-9)
      - Tallis's Street views in 1850 (reproductions; for originals see F128.65.A2T35-1854) (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Broadway (Bowling Green to Morris Street) (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - Broadway (Morris Street to Exchange Place) (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - Broadway (Exchange place - Wall Street/Rector) (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - Broadway (Wall street/Rector - Cedar street) (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - Broadway (Cedar street - Fulton street) (Box 11, Folder 6)
      - Broadway (Pedestrian Bridge at Fulton Street. Loew's Bridge) (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Broadway (Fulton street - Vesey/Ann street) (Box 12, Folder 2)
      - Broadway (Vesey/Ann street - City Hall Park) (Box 12, Folder 3)
      - Broadway (City Hall Park - Park Place) (Box 12, Folder 4)
      - Broadway (Park place - Chambers street) (Box 12, Folder 5)
      - Broadway (Chambers street - Worth street) (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Broadway (Worth street - Canal street) (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Broadway (Canal street - Broome street) (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Broadway (Broome street - Prince street) (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - Broadway (Prince street - Houston street) (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - Broadway (Houston street - 8th street) (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Broadway (8th street - 14th street) (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - Broadway (14th street - 23rd street) (Box 14, Folder 2)
      - Broadway (23rd street - 30th street) (Box 14, Folder 3)
      - Broadway (30th street - 36th street) (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - Broadway (36th street - 44th street folder 1) (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - Broadway (36th street - 44th street folder 2) (Box 14, Folder 6)
      - Broadway (44th street - 50th street) (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Broadway (50th street - 59th street) (Box 15, Folder 2)
      - Broadway (60th street - 72nd street) (Box 15, Folder 3)
      - Broadway (72nd street - 86th street) (Box 15, Folder 4)
      - Broadway (86th street - 100th street) (Box 15, Folder 5)
      - Broadway (100th street - 125th street) (Box 15, Folder 6)
      - Broadway (125th street - 150th street) (Box 15, Folder 7)
      - Broadway (150th street and north) (Box 15, Folder 8)
      - Broome Street (Box 15, Folder 9)
      - Burling Slip (see also John Street) (Box 15, Folder 10)
      - Byrd Street (Box 15, Folder 11)
      - Canal Street (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Carlisle street (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Caroline street (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - Catherine lane (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Catherine street (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - Cedar street (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - Central Park South (59th street and Fifth Avenue) (Box 16, Folder 8)
      - Central Park West (59th street to 110th street) (Box 16, Folder 9)
      - Centre Street (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Chambers Street (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - Charles Street (formerly Van Nest Place) (Box 16, Folder 12)
      - Charlton Street (Box 16, Folder 13)
      - Chatham Square (Box 16, Folder 14)
      - Cherry Street (Box 16, Folder 15)
      - Christopher Street (Box 16, Folder 16)
      - Church Street (Box 16, Folder 17)
      - Chrystie Street (Box 16, Folder 18)
      - City Hall Place (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Clendenning's Lane [closed] (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - Cliff Street (Box 17, Folder 3)
      - Clinton Street (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - Coenties Slip (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - Coffee House Slip (Box 17, Folder 6)
      - Collister Street (Box 17, Folder 7)
      - Columbia Avenue (Box 17, Folder 8)
      - Columbus Avenue (Box 17, Folder 9)
      - Commerce Avenue (Box 17, Folder 10)
      - Convent Avenue (Box 17, Folder 11)
      - Cooper Square (Box 17, Folder 12)
      - Cornelia Street (Box 17, Folder 13)
      - Cortlandt Street (Box 17, Folder 14)
      - Crosby Street (Box 17, Folder 15)
      - Delancey Street (Box 17, Folder 16)
      - Desbrosses Street (Box 17, Folder 17)
      - Dey Street (Box 17, Folder 18)
      - Division Street (Box 17, Folder 19)
      - Dominick Street (Box 17, Folder 20)
      - Donovan's Lane (Box 17, Folder 21)
      - Dover Street (Box 17, Folder 22)
      - Downing Place (Box 17, Folder 23)
      - Downing Street (Herring Farm) (Box 17, Folder 24)
      - Doyer(s) Street (Box 17, Folder 25)
      - Duane Street (Box 17, Folder 26)
      - Dutch Street (Box 17, Folder 27)
      - Dyckman Street (Box 17, Folder 28)
      - East Broadway (Box 17, Folder 29)
      - East End Avenue (Box 17, Folder 30)
      - East Houston (Box 17, Folder 31)
      - East River Drive (Box 17, Folder 32)
      - East Street (Box 17, Folder 33)
      - Edgar Street (Box 17, Folder 34)
      - Edgecombe Avenue (Box 17, Folder 35)
      - Eldridge Street (Box 18, Folder 1)